<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC0791 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC0793 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2474 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4271 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4303 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4360 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4364 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4456 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4456.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4760 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5668 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5668.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7153 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7153.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7223 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7223.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7606 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7606.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6811 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6811.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8205 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8205.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-idr-flow-spec-v6 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-flow-spec-v6.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.vandevelde-idr-flowspec-path-redirect SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.vandevelde-idr-flowspec-path-redirect.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-idr-rfc5575bis-17" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="5575,7674">
  <front>
   <title abbrev="RFC5575bis">Dissemination of Flow Specification Rules</title>
   <author fullname="Christoph Loibl" initials="C.L."
           surname="Loibl">
     <organization>Next Layer Communications</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Mariahilfer Guertel 37/7</street>
         <city>Vienna</city>
         <region></region>
         <code>1150</code>
         <country>AT</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+43 664 1176414</phone>
       <email>cl@tix.at</email>
     </address>
   </author>
    <author fullname="Susan Hares" initials="S" surname="Hares">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7453 Hickory Hill</street>
          <city>Saline</city>
          <region>MI</region>
          <code>48176</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shares@ndzh.com</email>
      </address>
	</author>
    <author fullname="Robert Raszuk" initials="R" surname="Raszuk">
      <organization>Bloomberg LP</organization>
	  <address>
        <postal>
         <street>731 Lexington Ave</street>
          <city>New York City</city>
          <region>NY</region>
          <code>10022</code>
		   <country>USA</country>
		</postal>
        <email>robert@raszuk.net </email>
      </address>
    </author>

	     <author fullname="Danny McPherson" initials="D" surname="McPherson">
      <organization>Verisign</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <code></code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dmcpherson@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

<author fullname="Martin Bacher" initials="M.B."
    surname="Bacher">
    <organization>T-Mobile Austria</organization>
    <address>
        <postal>
            <street>Rennweg 97-99</street>
            <city>Vienna</city>
            <region></region>
            <code>1030</code>
            <country>AT</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mb.ietf@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
</author>
    <date year="2019" />
    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <workgroup>IDR Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>RFC</keyword>
    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>Dissemination of Flow Specification Rules</keyword>
	<abstract>
	<t>
   This document defines a Border Gateway Protocol Network Layer
   Reachability Information (BGP NLRI) encoding format that can be used
   to distribute traffic Flow Specifications. This allows the routing
   system to propagate information regarding more specific components of
   the traffic aggregate defined by an IP destination prefix.
</t>
  <t>
   It specifies IPv4 traffic Flow Specifications via a BGP NLRI which
   carries a traffic Flow Specification filter, and an Extended community value
   which encodes actions a routing system can take if the packet matches the
   traffic flow filters. The flow filters and the actions are processed in a
   fixed order. Other drafts specify IPv6, MPLS addresses, L2VPN addresses, and
   NV03 encapsulation of IP addresses.
   </t>
   <t>
   This document obsoletes RFC5575 and RFC7674 to correct unclear specifications in the
   flow filters.
   </t>
   <t>
   Applications which use the bgp Flow Specification are:
   1) application which automate inter-domain coordination of traffic
   filtering, such as what is required in order to mitigate
   (distributed) denial-of-service attacks; 2) applications which
   control traffic filtering in the context of a BGP/MPLS VPN service,
   and 3) applications with centralized control of traffic in a SDN or NFV context.
   Some deployments of these three applications can be handled by
   the strict ordering of the BGP NLRI traffic flow filters, and the
   strict actions encoded in the extended community Flow Specification
   actions.
   </t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
	  <t>
	Modern IP routers contain both the capability to forward traffic
    according to IP prefixes as well as to classify, shape, rate limit,
    filter, or redirect packets based on administratively defined
    policies.
	  </t>
	  <t>
    These traffic policy mechanisms allow the router to define match
    rules that operate on multiple fields of the packet header.  Actions
    such as the ones described above can be associated with each rule.
	</t>
	<t>
    The n-tuple consisting of the matching criteria defines an aggregate
    traffic Flow Specification.  The matching criteria can include
    elements such as source and destination address prefixes, IP
    protocol, and transport protocol port numbers.
	</t>
	<t>
   This document defines a general procedure to encode flow
   specification rules for aggregated traffic flows so that they can be
   distributed as a BGP <xref target="RFC4271"></xref> NLRI.  Additionally, we define the
   required mechanisms to utilize this definition to the problem of
   immediate concern to the authors: intra- and inter-provider
   distribution of traffic filtering rules to filter (distributed)
   denial-of-service (DoS) attacks.
	</t>
	<t>
	 By expanding routing information with Flow Specifications, the
	routing system can take advantage of the ACL (Access Control List) or
	firewall capabilities in the router's forwarding path.  Flow
	specifications can be seen as more specific routing entries to a
	unicast prefix and are expected to depend upon the existing unicast
	data information.
	</t>
	<t>
	A Flow Specification received from an external autonomous system will
	need to be validated against unicast routing before being accepted.
	If the aggregate traffic flow defined by the unicast destination
   prefix is forwarded to a given BGP peer, then the local system can
   install more specific flow rules that may result in different
   forwarding behavior, as requested by this system.
	</t>
	<t>As with previous extensions to BGP, this specification makes it
   possible to add additional information to Internet routers.  These
   are limited in terms of the maximum number of data elements they can
   hold as well as the number of events they are able to process in a
   given unit of time. The authors believe that, as with previous
   extensions, service providers will be careful to keep information
   levels below the maximum capacity of their devices.
	</t>
	<t>
	Experience with previous BGP extensions has also shown that the
   maximum capacity of BGP speakers has been gradually increased
   according to expected loads. For example Internet unicast routing as
   well as other BGP applications increased their maximum capacity as they
   gain popularity.
   </t>
   <t>
   From an operational perspective, the utilization of BGP as the
   carrier for this information allows a network service provider to
   reuse both internal route distribution infrastructure (e.g., route
   reflector or confederation design) and existing external
   relationships (e.g., inter-domain BGP sessions to a customer
   network).
   </t>
   <t>
   While it is certainly possible to address this problem using other
   mechanisms, this solution has been utilized in deployments because of the
   substantial advantage of being an incremental addition to already
   deployed mechanisms.
   </t>
   <t>In current deployments, the information distributed by the flow-spec
   extension is originated both manually as well as automatically.  The
   latter by systems that are able to detect malicious flows.  When
   automated systems are used, care should be taken to ensure their
   correctness as well as to limit the number and advertisement rate of
   flow routes (see also <xref target="security_considerations" />).
   </t>
   <t>
   This specification defines required protocol extensions to address
   most common applications of IPv4 unicast and VPNv4 unicast filtering.
   The same mechanism can be reused and new match criteria added to
   address similar filtering needs for other BGP address families such as
   IPv6 families <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flow-spec-v6"></xref>.
   </t>
    </section>
	<section title="Definitions of Terms Used in This Memo">
	<t>
	<list style="hanging">
	<t hangText="NLRI - ">Network Layer Reachability Information.
	</t>
	<t hangText="RIB - ">Routing Information Base.
	</t>
	<t hangText="Loc-RIB - ">
        The Loc-RIB contains the routes that have been selected by the
        local BGP speaker's Decision Process.
	</t>
	<t hangText="AS - ">Autonomous System.
	</t>
	<t hangText="VRF - ">Virtual Routing and Forwarding instance.
	</t>
    <t hangText="PE - ">Provider Edge router
	</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref>
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Flow Specifications">
	<t>
	 A Flow Specification is an n-tuple consisting of several matching
	criteria that can be applied to IP traffic.  A given IP packet is
	said to match the defined flow if it matches all the specified
	criteria. This n-tuple is encoded into a BGP NLRI defined below.
	</t>
  <t>

  </t>
	<t>A given flow may be associated with a set of attributes, depending on
   the particular application; such attributes may or may not include
   reachability information (i.e., NEXT_HOP).  Well-known or AS-specific
   community attributes can be used to encode a set of predetermined
   actions.
   </t>
   <t>
     A particular application is identified by a specific (Address Family
     Identifier, Subsequent Address Family Identifier (AFI, SAFI)) pair <xref
     target="RFC4760"></xref> and corresponds to a distinct set of RIBs.  Those
     RIBs should be treated independently from each other in order to assure
     non-interference between distinct applications.
   </t>
   <t>
     BGP itself treats the NLRI as a key to an entry in its
     databases.  Entries that are placed in the Loc-RIB are then
     associated with a given set of semantics, which is application
     dependent.  This is consistent with existing BGP applications.  For
     instance, IP unicast routing (AFI=1, SAFI=1) and IP multicast
     reverse-path information (AFI=1, SAFI=2) are handled by BGP without
     any particular semantics being associated with them until installed
     in the Loc-RIB.
	</t>
	<t>
   Standard BGP policy mechanisms, such as UPDATE filtering by NLRI
   prefix as well as community matching and manipulation, must apply to the Flow Specification
   defined NLRI-type, especially in an inter-domain environment.
   Network operators can also control propagation of such
   routing updates by enabling or disabling the exchange of a particular
   (AFI, SAFI) pair on a given BGP peering session.
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Dissemination of IPv4 FLow Specification Information" anchor="dissemination_ipv4_flowspec">
	<t>
	We define a "Flow Specification" NLRI type (<xref target="fs_nlri" />)
  that may include several components such as destination prefix,
  source prefix, protocol, ports, and others (see
  <xref target="nlri_value_encoding" /> below).
 	</t>
	<t>
	 This NLRI information is encoded using MP_REACH_NLRI and
	MP_UNREACH_NLRI attributes as defined in  <xref target="RFC4760"></xref>.
	Whenever the corresponding application does not require Next Hop
	information, this shall be encoded as a 0-octet length Next Hop in
	the MP_REACH_NLRI attribute (if a non 0-octet Next Hop is present
    it should be ignored on receipt).
	</t>
	<t>
	 The NLRI field of the MP_REACH_NLRI and MP_UNREACH_NLRI is encoded as
	a 1- or 2-octet NLRI length field followed by a variable-length NLRI
	value.  The NLRI length is expressed in octets.
	</t>
	<t>
	<figure title="Flow-spec NLRI for IPv4" anchor="fs_nlri">
	<artwork>
                    +------------------------------+
                    |    length (0xnn or 0xfnnn)   |
                    +------------------------------+
                    |    NLRI value  (variable)    |
                    +------------------------------+
	</artwork>
	</figure>
	</t>
   <t>
   Implementations wishing to exchange Flow Specification rules MUST use
   BGP's Capability Advertisement facility to exchange the Multiprotocol
   Extension Capability Code (Code 1) as defined in <xref target="RFC4760"></xref>.
   The (AFI, SAFI) pair carried in the Multiprotocol Extension
   Capability MUST be (AFI=1, SAFI=133) for IPv4 Flow Specification, and
   (AFI=1, SAFI=134) for VPNv4 Flow Specification.
   </t>
	<section title="Length Encoding">
    <t>
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>If the NLRI length is smaller than 240 (0xf0 hex) octets, the length
   field can be encoded as a single octet.  </t>
    <t>Otherwise, it is encoded as
    an extended-length 2-octet value in which the most significant nibble
    of the first byte is all ones.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>
	 In figure 1 above, values less-than 240 are encoded using two hex
	digits (0xnn).  Values above 239 are encoded using 3 hex digits
	(0xfnnn).  The highest value that can be represented with this
	encoding is 4095. For example the length value of 239 is encoded as 0xef (single octet)
    while 240 is encoded as 0xf0f0 (2-octet).
	</t>
	</section>
	<section anchor="nlri_value_encoding" title="NLRI Value Encoding">
	<t>
    The Flow Specification NLRI-type consists of several optional
   subcomponents.  A specific packet is considered to match the flow
   specification when it matches the intersection (AND) of all the
   components present in the specification.
  </t>
   <t>
     The encoding of each of the NLRI components begins with a type field
     (1 octet) followed by a variable length parameter. <xref target="type_1" />
     to <xref target="type_12" />
     define component types and parameter encodings for the IPv4 IP layer and
     transport layer headers. IPv6 NLRI component types are described
     in <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-flow-spec-v6"></xref>.
   </t>
   <t>
   Flow Specification components must follow strict type ordering by increasing
   numerical order. A given component type may (exactly once) or may not be
   present in the specification. If present, it MUST precede any component of
   higher numeric type value.
   </t>
   <t>
       All combinations of component types within a single NLRI are allowed. However,
       some combinations cannot match any packets (ie. "ICMP Type AND Port" will never
       match any packets), and thus SHOULD not be propagated by BGP.
   </t>
<section anchor="type_1" title="Type 1 - Destination Prefix">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding: &lt;type (1 octet), length (1 octet), prefix (variable)>
</t>
<t>Defines the destination prefix to match. The length and prefix fields are
encoded as in BGP UPDATE messages <xref target="RFC4271" />
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_2" title="Type 2 - Source Prefix">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding: &lt;type (1 octet), length (1 octet), prefix (variable)&gt;
</t>
<t>Defines the source prefix to match. The length and prefix fields are
encoded as in BGP UPDATE messages <xref target="RFC4271" />
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_3" title="Type 3 - IP Protocol">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, value]+&gt;
</t>
<t>Contains a set of {operator, value} pairs that are used to
match the IP protocol value byte in IP packets.
</t>
<t>The operator byte is encoded as:
<figure>
<artwork>
                      0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
                    +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
                    | e | a |  len  | 0 |lt |gt |eq |
                    +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+

                            Numeric operator
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>e - end-of-list bit.  Set in the last {op, value} pair in the list.
</t>
<t>a - AND bit.  If unset, the previous term is logically ORed with the current
one.  If set, the operation is a logical AND. In the first operator byte of a sequence
it SHOULD be encoded as unset and and MUST be treated as always unset on decoding.
The AND operator has higher priority than OR for
the purposes of evaluating logical expressions.
</t>
<t>len - length of the value field for this operator given as (1 &lt;&lt; len). This
  encodes 1 (len=00), 2 (len=01), 4 (len=10), 8 (len=11) bytes.
  Type 3 flow component values SHOULD be encoded as single byte (len=00).
</t>
<t>0 - SHOULD be set to 0 on NLRI encoding, and MUST be ignored during decoding
</t>
<t>lt - less than comparison between data and value.
</t>
<t>gt - greater than comparison between data and value.
</t>
<t>eq - equality between data and value.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
  The bits lt, gt, and eq can be combined to produce common
       relational operators such as "less or equal", "greater or equal",
       and "not equal to" as shown in <xref target="table_comparison_operator" />.
</t>
    <texttable anchor="table_comparison_operator" title="Comparison operation combinations">
        <ttcol align="center">lt</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">gt</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">eq</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Resulting operation</ttcol>
        <c>0</c><c>0</c><c>0</c><c> false (independent of the value)</c>
        <c>0</c><c>0</c><c>1</c><c> == (equal) </c>
        <c>0</c><c>1</c><c>0</c><c> &gt; (greater than) </c>
        <c>0</c><c>1</c><c>1</c><c> &gt;= (greater than or equal)</c>
        <c>1</c><c>0</c><c>0</c><c> &lt; (less than)</c>
        <c>1</c><c>0</c><c>1</c><c> &lt;= (less than or equal)</c>
        <c>1</c><c>1</c><c>0</c><c> != (not equal value)</c>
        <c>1</c><c>1</c><c>1</c><c> true (independent of the value)</c>
    </texttable>

</section>
<section anchor="type_4" title="Type 4 - Port">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, value]+&gt;
</t>
<t>Defines a list of {operator, value} pairs that matches source
   OR destination TCP/UDP ports (see <xref target="RFC0793" /> Section 3.1).
   This component matches if either the destination port OR the source port
   of a flow matches the value. This list is encoded using the
   numeric operator format defined in <xref target="type_3" />.
   Values SHOULD be encoded as 1- or 2-byte quantities.
</t>
<t>
    In case of the presence of the port (destination-port, source-port)
    component only TCP or UDP packets can match the entire Flow Specification Rule.
    The port component, if present, never matches when the packet's IP
    protocol value is not 6 (TCP) or 17 (UDP), if the packet is fragmented
    and this is not the first fragement, or if the system is unable to
    locate the transport header. Different implementations may or may not be
    able to decode the transport header in the presence of IP
    options or Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) NULL
    <xref target="RFC4303"></xref> encryption.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_5" title="Type 5 - Destination Port">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, value]+&gt;
</t>
<t> Defines a list of {operator, value} pairs used to match the
    destination port of a TCP or UDP packet (see also <xref target="RFC0793" /> Section 3.1).
    This list is encoded using the numeric operator format defined in <xref target="type_3" />.
    Values SHOULD be encoded as 1- or 2-byte quantities.
</t>
<t>The last paragraph of <xref target="type_4" /> also applies to this component.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_6" title="Type 6 - Source Port">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, value]+&gt;
</t>
<t>  Defines a list of {operator, value} pairs used to match the
    source port of a TCP or UDP packet (see also <xref target="RFC0793" /> Section 3.1).
    This list is encoded using the numeric operator format defined in <xref target="type_3" />.
    Values SHOULD be encoded as 1- or 2-byte quantities.
</t>
<t>The last paragraph of <xref target="type_4" /> also applies to this component.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_7" title="Type 7 - ICMP type">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, value]+&gt;
</t>
<t>Defines a list of {operator, value} pairs used to match the
type field of an ICMP packet. This list is encoded using the
numeric operator format defined in <xref target="type_3" />.
Values SHOULD be encoded using a single byte.
</t>
<t>The ICMP type specifiers evaluate to FALSE whenever
the protocol value is not ICMP.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_8" title="Type 8 - ICMP code">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, value]+&gt;
</t>
<t>
Defines a list of {operator, value} pairs used to match the
code field of an ICMP packet. This list is encoded using the
numeric operator format defined in <xref target="type_3" />.
Values SHOULD be encoded using a single byte.
</t>
<t>The ICMP code specifiers evaluate to FALSE whenever
the protocol value is not ICMP.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_9" title="Type 9 - TCP flags">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, bitmask]+&gt;
</t>
<t>Bitmask values can be encoded as a 1- or 2-byte bitmask.  When
a single byte is specified, it matches byte 13 of the TCP
header <xref target="RFC0793"></xref>, which contains
bits 8 though 15 of the 4th 32-bit word.
When a 2-byte encoding is used, it matches bytes
12 and 13 of the TCP header with the data offset field having a
"don't care" value.
</t>
<t>
This component evaluates to FALSE for packets that are not TCP packets.
</t>
<t>This type uses the bitmask operator format, which differs from
the numeric operator format in the lower nibble.
<figure>
<artwork>
                  0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
                +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
                | e | a |  len  | 0 | 0 |not| m |
                +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+

                        Bitmask operator
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="e, a, len - Most significant nibble:"> (end-of-list bit, AND
 bit, and length field), as defined for in the numeric operator format in <xref target="type_3" />.
</t>
<t hangText="not - NOT bit."> If set, logical negation of operation.
</t>
<t hangText="m -   Match bit."> If set, this is a bitwise match operation
defined as "(data AND value) == value"; if unset, (data AND value) evaluates
to TRUE if any of the bits in the value mask are set in the data
</t>
<t hangText="0 -   all 0 bits"> SHOULD be set to 0 on NLRI encoding, and MUST be ignored during decoding
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_10" title="Type 10 - Packet length">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, value]+&gt;
</t>
<t>
  Defines a list of {operator, value} pairs used to match on the total
  IP packet length (excluding Layer 2 but including IP header). This list
  is encoded using the numeric operator format defined in
  <xref target="type_3" />. Values SHOULD be encoded using 1- or 2-byte
  quantities.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_11" title="Type 11 -  DSCP (Diffserv Code Point)">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, value]+&gt;
</t>
<t> Defines a list of {operator, value} pairs used to match the
6-bit DSCP field <xref target="RFC2474"></xref>.
This list is encoded using the numeric operator format defined in
<xref target="type_3" />. Values SHOULD be encoded using a single byte.
The six least significant bits contain the DSCP value. All other bits SHOULD be encoded
as zero and ignored on decoding.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="type_12" title="Type 12 - Fragment">
<t>
<list>
<t>Encoding:&lt;type (1 octet), [op, bitmask]+&gt;
</t>
<t> Uses bitmask operator format defined in <xref target="type_9" />.
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
                   0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
                 +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
                 | 0 | 0 | 0 | 0 |LF |FF |IsF|DF |
                 +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>Bitmask values:
<list style="symbol">
<t>Bit 7 - Don't fragment (DF) - match if <xref target="RFC0791" /> IP Header Flags Bit-1 (DF) is 1
</t>
<t>Bit 6 - Is a fragment (IsF) - match if <xref target="RFC0791" /> IP Header Fragment Offset is not 0
</t>
<t>Bit 5 - First fragment (FF) - match if <xref target="RFC0791" /> IP Header Fragment Offset is 0 AND Flags Bit-2 (MF) is 1
</t>
<t>Bit 4 - Last fragment (LF) - match if <xref target="RFC0791" /> IP Header Fragment Offset is not 0 AND Flags Bit-2 (MF) is 0
</t>
<t>Bit 0-3 - SHOULD be set to 0 on NLRI encoding, and MUST be ignored during decoding
</t>
</list>
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
<section title="Examples of Encodings">
 <section title="Example 1">
<t>
 An example of a Flow Specification encoding for: "all packets to
    192.0.2.0/24 and TCP port 25".
</t>
 <t>
 <figure>
 <artwork>
       +------------------+----------+----------+
       | destination      | protocol | port     |
       +------------------+----------+----------+
       | 0x01 18 c0 00 02 | 03 81 06 | 04 81 19 |
       +------------------+----------+----------+
 </artwork>
 </figure>
 </t>
<t>
   Decode for protocol (type 3):
<figure>
<artwork>
       +-------+----------+------------------------------+
       | Value |          |                              |
       +-------+----------+------------------------------+
       |  0x03 | type     |                              |
       |  0x81 | operator | end-of-list, value size=1, = |
       |  0x06 | value    |                              |
       +-------+----------+------------------------------+
</artwork>
</figure>
   Decode for port (type 4):
<figure>
<artwork>
       +-------+----------+------------------------------+
       | Value |          |                              |
       +-------+----------+------------------------------+
       |  0x04 | type     |                              |
       |  0x81 | operator | end-of-list, value size=1, = |
       |  0x19 | value    |                              |
       +-------+----------+------------------------------+
</artwork>
</figure>
    This constitutes an NLRI with an NLRI length of 11 octets.
</t>
</section>
 <section title="Example 2">
     <t>
   An example of a Flow Specification encoding for: "all packets to
   192.0.2.0/24 from 203.0.113.0/24 and port {range [137, 139] or 8080}".
<figure>
<artwork>
       +------------------+----------------+-------------------------+
       | destination      | source         | port                    |
       +------------------+----------------+-------------------------+
       | 0x01 18 c0 00 02 | 02 18 cb 00 71 | 04 03 89 45 8b 91 1f 90 |
       +------------------+----------------+-------------------------+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Decode for port (type 4):
<figure>
<artwork>
       +--------+----------+------------------------------+
       |  Value |          |                              |
       +--------+----------+------------------------------+
       |   0x04 | type     |                              |
       |   0x03 | operator | value size=1, &gt;=             |
       |   0x89 | value    | 137                          |
       |   0x45 | operator | "AND", value size=1, &lt;=      |
       |   0x8b | value    | 139                          |
       |   0x91 | operator | end-of-list, value size=2, = |
       | 0x1f90 | value    | 8080                         |
       +--------+----------+------------------------------+
</artwork>
</figure>
This constitutes an NLRI with an NLRI length of 18 octets.
</t>
</section>
 <section title="Example 3">
     <t>
   An example of a Flow Specification encoding for: "all packets to
   192.0.2.1/32 and fragment { DF or FF } (matching packet with DF bit set or First Fragments)
<figure>
<artwork>
       +---------------------+----------+
       | destination         | fragment |
       +---------------------+----------+
       | 0x01 20 c0 00 02 01 | 0c 80 05 |
       +---------------------+----------+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Decode for fragment (type 12):
<figure>
<artwork>
       +--------+----------+------------------------------+
       |  Value |          |                              |
       +--------+----------+------------------------------+
       |   0x0c | type     |                              |
       |   0x80 | operator | end-of-list, value size=1    |
       |   0x05 | value    | DF=1, FF=1                   |
       +--------+----------+------------------------------+
</artwork>
</figure>
This constitutes an NLRI with an NLRI length of 9 octets.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="traffic_filtering" title="Traffic Filtering">
    <t>
   Traffic filtering policies have been traditionally considered to be relatively
 static.  Limitations of these static mechanisms caused this new dynamic mechanism to be
 designed for the three new applications of traffic filtering:
    <list style="symbols">
        <t>Prevention of traffic-based, denial-of-service (DOS) attacks.</t>
        <t>Traffic filtering in the context of BGP/MPLS VPN service.</t>
        <t>Centralized traffic control for SDN/NFV networks.</t>
    </list>
 These application require coordination among service providers and/or coordination
 among the AS within a service provider.  <xref target="limitations_previous" /> has details on the
 limitation of previous mechanisms and why BGP Flow Specification
 provides a solution to prevent DOS and aid BGP/MPLS VPN filtering rules.
	</t>
	<t>
	The Flow Specification NLRI defined above to convey information about traffic
filtering rules for traffic that should be discarded or handled in manner
specified by a set of pre-defined actions (which are defined in BGP Extended
Communities). This mechanism is primarily designed to allow an upstream
autonomous system to perform inbound filtering in their ingress routers of
traffic that a given downstream AS wishes to drop.
   </t>
   <t>
   In order to achieve this goal, this draft specifies two application specific
   NLRI identifiers that provide traffic filters, and a set of actions encoding
   in BGP Extended Communities.  The two application specific NLRI identifiers
   are:
   <list style="symbols">
   <t>
     IPv4 Flow Specification identifier (AFI=1, SAFI=133) along with specific
     semantic rules for IPv4 routes, and
   </t>
   <t>
     VPNv4 Flow Specification identifier (AFI=1, SAFI=134)
     value, which can be used to propagate traffic filtering information
     in a BGP/MPLS VPN environment.
   </t>
   </list>
   </t>
   <t>
       Encoding of the NLRI is described in <xref target="dissemination_ipv4_flowspec" /> for IPv4 Flow Specification and   in
       <xref target="traffic_filtering_vpn" /> for VPNv4 Flow Specification. The filtering actions are described
       in <xref target="traffic_filtering_actions" />.
   </t>
<section title="Ordering of Traffic Filtering Rules">
<t>
   With traffic filtering rules, more than one rule may match a
   particular traffic flow.  Thus, it is necessary to define the order
   at which rules get matched and applied to a particular traffic flow.
   This ordering function must be such that it must not depend on the
   arrival order of the Flow Specification's rules and must be consistent
   in the network.
</t>
<t>
   The relative order of two Flow Specification rules is determined by
   comparing their respective components.  The algorithm starts by
   comparing the left-most components of the rules.  If the types
   differ, the rule with lowest numeric type value has higher precedence
   (and thus will match before) than the rule that doesn't contain that
   component type.  If the component types are the same, then a type-
   specific comparison is performed (see below) if the types are equal the
   algorithm continues with the next component.
</t>
<t>
  For IP prefix values (IP destination or source prefix): If the prefixes
  overlap, the one with the longer prefix-length has higher precedence. If they
  do not overlap the one with the lowest IP value has higher precedence.
</t>
<t>
   For all other component types, unless otherwise specified, the comparison is
   performed by comparing the component data as a binary string using the
   memcmp() function as defined by <xref target="ISO_IEC_9899" />. For strings with equal
   lengths the lowest string (memcmp) has higher precedence. For strings of
   different lengths, the common prefix is compared. If the common prefix is not
   equal the string with the lowest prefix has higher precedence. If the common
   prefix is equal, the longest string is considered to have higher precedence
   than the shorter one.
</t>

<t>
  The code below shows a Python3 implementation of the comparison
  algorithm. The full code was tested with Python 3.6.3 and can be
  obtained at <eref target="https://github.com/stoffi92/flowspec-cmp">https://github.com/stoffi92/flowspec-cmp</eref>.
</t>
<t>
  <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS>
import itertools
import ipaddress

def flow_rule_cmp(a, b):
    for comp_a, comp_b in itertools.zip_longest(a.components,
                                           b.components):
        # If a component type does not exist in one rule
        # this rule has lower precedence
        if not comp_a:
            return B_HAS_PRECEDENCE
        if not comp_b:
            return A_HAS_PRECEDENCE
        # higher precedence for lower component type
        if comp_a.component_type < comp_b.component_type:
            return A_HAS_PRECEDENCE
        if comp_a.component_type > comp_b.component_type:
            return B_HAS_PRECEDENCE
        # component types are equal -> type specific comparison
        if comp_a.component_type in (IP_DESTINATION, IP_SOURCE):
            # assuming comp_a.value, comp_b.value of type ipaddress
            if comp_a.value.overlaps(comp_b.value):
                # longest prefixlen has precedence
                if comp_a.value.prefixlen > comp_b.value.prefixlen:
                    return A_HAS_PRECEDENCE
                if comp_a.value.prefixlen < comp_b.value.prefixlen:
                    return B_HAS_PRECEDENCE
                # components equal -> continue with next component
            elif comp_a.value > comp_b.value:
                return B_HAS_PRECEDENCE
            elif comp_a.value < comp_b.value:
                return A_HAS_PRECEDENCE
        else:
            # assuming comp_a.value, comp_b.value of type bytearray
            if len(comp_a.value) == len(comp_b.value):
                if comp_a.value > comp_b.value:
                    return B_HAS_PRECEDENCE
                if comp_a.value < comp_b.value:
                    return A_HAS_PRECEDENCE
                # components equal -> continue with next component
            else:
                common = min(len(comp_a.value), len(comp_b.value))
                if comp_a.value[:common] > comp_b.value[:common]:
                    return B_HAS_PRECEDENCE
                elif comp_a.value[:common] < comp_b.value[:common]:
                    return A_HAS_PRECEDENCE
                # the first common bytes match
                elif len(comp_a.value) > len(comp_b.value):
                    return A_HAS_PRECEDENCE
                else:
                    return B_HAS_PRECEDENCE
    return EQUAL
<CODE ENDS>
    ]]></artwork>
  </figure>
</t>
</section>
	</section>
<section title="Validation Procedure" anchor="validation_procedure">
<t>Flow Specifications received from a BGP peer that are accepted in
   the respective Adj-RIB-In are used as input to the route selection
   process.  Although the forwarding attributes of two routes for the
   same Flow Specification prefix may be the same, BGP is still required
   to perform its path selection algorithm in order to select the
   correct set of attributes to advertise.
</t>
<t>
   The first step of the BGP Route Selection procedure (Section 9.1.2 of
   <xref target="RFC4271"></xref> is to exclude from the
   selection procedure routes that are
   considered non-feasible.  In the context of IP routing information,
   this step is used to validate that the NEXT_HOP attribute of a given
   route is resolvable.
</t>
<t>
   The concept can be extended, in the case of the Flow Specification NLRI,
   to allow other validation procedures.
</t>
<t>
   A Flow Specification NLRI must be validated such that it is
   considered feasible if and only if all of the below is true:
<list>
<t>
  a) A destination prefix component is embedded in the Flow Specification.
</t>
<t>
  b) The originator of the Flow Specification matches the originator of
  the best-match unicast route for the destination prefix embedded
  in the Flow Specification (this is the unicast route with the longest
    possible prefix length covering the destination prefix embedded in
    the Flow Specification).
</t>
<t>
  c) There are no more specific unicast routes, when compared with the
  flow destination prefix, that have been received from a different
  neighboring AS than the best-match unicast route, which has been
  determined in rule b).
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
  Rule a) MAY be relaxed by configuration, permitting Flow
  Specifications that include no destination prefix component. If such
  is the case, rules b) and c) are moot and MUST be disregarded.
</t>
<t>
   By originator of a BGP route, we mean either the address of the
    originator in the ORIGINATOR_ID Attribute <xref target="RFC4456" />,
    or the source IP address of the BGP peer, if this path attribute is
    not present.
</t>
<t>
   BGP implementations MUST also enforce that the AS_PATH attribute of a
   route received via the External Border Gateway Protocol (eBGP)
   contains the neighboring AS in the left-most position of the AS_PATH
   attribute.  While this rule is optional in the BGP specification, it
   becomes necessary to enforce it for security reasons.
</t>
<t>
The best-match unicast route may change over the time independently of the
Flow Specification NLRI.  Therefore, a revalidation of the Flow Specification
NLRI MUST be performed whenever unicast routes change.  Revalidation is
defined as retesting that clause a and clause b above are true.
</t>
<t>Explanation:
</t>
<t>
   The underlying concept is that the neighboring AS that advertises the
   best unicast route for a destination is allowed to advertise flow-
   spec information that conveys a more or equally specific destination
   prefix.  Thus, as long as there are no more specific unicast routes,
   received from a different neighboring AS, which would be affected by
   that filtering rule.
</t>
<t>
   The neighboring AS is the immediate destination of the traffic
   described by the Flow Specification.  If it requests these flows to
   be dropped, that request can be honored without concern that it
   represents a denial of service in itself.  Supposedly, the traffic is
   being dropped by the downstream autonomous system, and there is no
   added value in carrying the traffic to it.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="traffic_filtering_actions" title="Traffic Filtering Actions">
<t>
   This specification defines a minimum set of filtering actions that it
   standardizes as BGP extended community values <xref target="RFC4360"></xref>.
   This is not meant to be an inclusive list of all the possible actions, but only a
   subset that can be interpreted consistently across the network.
   Additional actions can be defined as either requiring standards or
   as vendor specific.
 </t>
 <t>
    Implementations SHOULD provide mechanisms that map an arbitrary BGP
   community value (normal or extended) to filtering actions that
   require different mappings in different systems in the network.  For
   instance, providing packets with a worse-than-best-effort, per-hop
   behavior is a functionality that is likely to be implemented
   differently in different systems and for which no standard behavior
   is currently known.  Rather than attempting to define it here, this
   can be accomplished by mapping a user-defined community value to
   platform-/network-specific behavior via user configuration.
 </t>
 <t>
    The default action for a traffic filtering Flow Specification is to
   accept IP traffic that matches that particular rule.
 </t>
 <t>This document defines the following extended communities values
 shown in <xref target="traffic_extended_communities" /> in the form
 0x8xnn where nn indicates the sub-type. Encodings for these extended
 communities are described below.
 </t>
   <texttable anchor="traffic_extended_communities" title="Traffic Action
     Extended Communities">
       <ttcol align="left">community</ttcol>
       <ttcol align="left">action</ttcol>
       <ttcol align="left">encoding</ttcol>
       <c>0x8006</c> <c>traffic-rate-bytes</c>      <c>2-byte ASN, 4-byte float</c>
       <c>TBD</c>    <c>traffic-rate-packets</c>    <c>2-byte ASN, 4-byte float</c>
       <c>0x8007</c> <c>traffic-action</c>          <c>bitmask</c>
       <c>0x8008</c> <c>rt-redirect AS-2byte</c>  <c>2-octet AS, 4-octet value</c>
       <c>0x8108</c> <c>rt-redirect IPv4</c>      <c>4-octet IPv4 addres, 2-octet value</c>
       <c>0x8208</c> <c>rt-redirect AS-4byte</c>  <c>4-octet AS, 2-octet value</c>
       <c>0x8009</c> <c>traffic-marking</c>         <c>DSCP value</c>
   </texttable>
 <t>
 Some traffic action communities may interfere with each other.
 <xref target="rules_action_interference" /> of this specification
 provides general considerations on such traffic action interference.
 Any additional definition of a traffic actions specified
 by additional standards documents or vendor documents
 MUST specify if the traffic action interacts with an
 existing traffic actions, and provide error handling
 per <xref target="RFC7606"></xref>.
</t>
<t>
Multiple traffic actions may be present for a single NLRI.  The traffic
actions are processed in ascending order of the sub-type found in the BGP
Extended Communities. If not all of them can be processed the filter SHALL NOT
be applied at all (for example: if for a given flow there are the action communities
rate-limit-bytes and traffic-marking attached, and the plattform does not support
one of them also the other shall not be applied for that flow).
</t>
<t>
All traffic actions are specified as transitive BGP Extended
Communities.
</t>
 <section title="Traffic Rate in Bytes (traffic-rate-bytes) sub-type 0x06">
 <t>The traffic-rate-bytes extended community uses the following
   extended community encoding:
 </t>
<t>
 The first two octets carry the 2-octet id, which can be
 assigned from a 2-byte AS number.  When a 4-byte AS number is
 locally present, the 2 least significant bytes of such an AS
 number can be used.  This value is purely informational and
 SHOULD NOT be interpreted by the implementation.
</t>
<t>
The remaining 4 octets carry the maximum rate information in IEEE floating point
<xref target="IEEE.754.1985"></xref> format, units being bytes per second.  A
traffic-rate of 0 should result on all traffic for the particular flow to be
discarded. On encoding the traffic-rate MUST NOT be negative. On
decoding negative values MUST be treated as zero (discard all traffic).
 </t>
 <t>Interferes with: No other BGP Flow Specification traffic action in
 this document.</t>
</section>
<section anchor="traffic_rate_in_packets" title="Traffic Rate in Packets (traffic-rate-packets) sub-type TBD">
<t>
  The traffic-rate-packets extended community uses the same encoding as the
  traffic-rate-bytes extended community. The floating point value carries the
  maximum packet rate in packets per second. A traffic-rate-packets of 0 should
  result in all traffic for the particular flow to be discarded. On encoding the
  traffic-rate-packets MUST NOT be negative.  On decoding negative values MUST
  be treated as zero (discard all traffic).
</t>
<t>Interferes with: No other BGP Flow Specification traffic action in
this document.</t>
</section>
 <section anchor="traffic_action_subtype" title="Traffic-action (traffic-action) sub-type 0x07">
 <t>The traffic-action extended community consists of 6
      bytes of which only the 2 least significant bits of the 6th byte
      (from left to right) are currently defined.
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |   reserved    |   reserved    |   reserved    |   reserved    |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |   reserved    | reserved  |S|T|
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>where S and T are defined as:
<list style="symbols">
<t>T: Terminal Action (bit 47): When this bit is set, the traffic
   filtering engine will apply any subsequent filtering rules (as
   defined by the ordering procedure).  If not set, the evaluation
   of the traffic filter stops when this rule is applied.
</t>
<t>S: Sample (bit 46): Enables traffic sampling and logging for this
     Flow Specification.
</t>
<t>reserved: should always be set to 0 by the originator and not be evaluated
  by the receiving BGP speaker.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
  The use of the Terminal Action (bit 47) may result in more than one
  filter-rule matching a particular flow. All the flow actions from these rules
  shall be collected and applied. In case of interfering traffic actions
  it is an implementation decision which actions are selected. See also <xref
  target="rules_action_interference" />.
</t>
<t>Interferes with: No other BGP Flow Specification traffic action in
this document.
</t>
</section>
 <section anchor="rt_redirect_action_subtype" title="RT Redirect (rt-redirect) sub-type 0x08">
 <t>The redirect extended community allows the traffic to be
  redirected to a VRF routing instance that lists the specified
  route-target in its import policy. If several local instances
  match this criteria, the choice between them is a local matter
  (for example, the instance with the lowest Route Distinguisher
  value can be elected).  This extended community allows 3 different
  encodings formats for the route-target (type 0x80, 0x81, 0x82).
  Is uses the same encoding as the Route Target extended community [RFC4360].
</t>
<t>
   It should be noted that the low-order nibble of the Redirect's Type
   field corresponds to the Route Target Extended Community format field
   (Type).  (See Sections 3.1, 3.2, and 4 of <xref target="RFC4360"></xref>
   plus Section 2 of <xref target="RFC5668"></xref>.)
   The low-order octet (Sub-Type) of the Redirect Extended
   Community remains 0x08 for all three encodings of the
   BGP Extended Communities (AS 2-byte, AS 4-byte, and IPv4 address).
</t>
<t>Interferes with: All other redirect functions.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Traffic Marking (traffic-marking) sub-type 0x09">
<t> The traffic marking extended community instructs a
 system to modify the DSCP bits of a transiting IP packet to the
 corresponding value.  This extended community is encoded as a
 sequence of 5 zero bytes followed by the DSCP value encoded in the
 6 least significant bits of 6th byte.
 </t>
 <t>Interferes with: No other BGP Flow Specification traffic action in
 this document.</t>
</section>
 <section anchor="rules_action_interference" title="Considerations on Traffic Action Interference">
<t>
   Since traffic actions are represented as BGP extended community values,
   traffic actions may interfere with each other (e.g. there may be more than
   one conflicting traffic-rate action associated with a single
   flow-filter). Traffic action interference has no impact on BGP propagation
   of flow filters (all communities are propagated according to policies).
</t>
<t>
   If a flow filter associated with interfering flow actions is selected for
   packet forwarding, it is a implementation decision which of the interfering
   traffic actions are selected. Implementors of this specification SHOULD
   document the behaviour of their implementation in such cases.
</t>
<t>
   If required, operators are encouraged to make use of the BGP policy framework
   supported by their implementation in order to achieve a predictable behaviour
   (ie. match - replace - delete communities on administrative boundaries).
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="traffic_filtering_vpn" title="Dissemination of Traffic Filtering in BGP/MPLS VPN Networks">
<t>
   Provider-based Layer 3 VPN networks, such as the ones using a BGP/ MPLS IP
   VPN <xref target="RFC4364"></xref> control plane, may have different traffic
   filtering requirements than Internet service providers. But also Internet
   service providers may use those VPNs for scenarios like having the Internet
   routing table in a VRF, resulting in the same traffic filtering requirements
   as defined for the global routing table environment within this document.
   This document defines an additional BGP NLRI type (AFI=1, SAFI=134) value,
   which can be used to propagate traffic filtering information in a BGP/MPLS
   VPN environment.
 </t>
<t>
   The NLRI format for this address family consists of a fixed-length Route
   Distinguisher field (8 bytes) followed by a Flow Specification, following the
   encoding defined above in <xref target="nlri_value_encoding" /> of this
   document.  The NLRI length field shall include both the 8 bytes of the Route
   Distinguisher as well as the subsequent Flow Specification.
</t>
<t>
<figure title="Flow-spec NLRI for MPLS">
  <artwork>
                    +------------------------------+
                    | length (0xnn or 0xfn nn)     |
                    +------------------------------+
                    | Route Distinguisher (8 bytes)|
                    +------------------------------+
                    |    NLRI value  (variable)    |
                    +------------------------------+
  </artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
   Propagation of this NLRI is controlled by matching Route Target
   extended communities associated with the BGP path advertisement with
   the VRF import policy, using the same mechanism as described in BGP/
   MPLS IP VPNs <xref target="RFC4364"></xref>.
</t>
<t>
   Flow Specification rules received via this NLRI apply only to traffic
   that belongs to the VRF(s) in which it is imported. By default,
   traffic received from a remote PE is switched via an MPLS forwarding
   decision and is not subject to filtering.
</t>
<t>
   Contrary to the behavior specified for the non-VPN NLRI, flow rules
   are accepted by default, when received from remote PE routers.
</t>
<t>
    The validation procedure (<xref target="validation_procedure" />) and
    traffic filtering actions (<xref target="traffic_filtering_actions" />) are the same as
    for IPv4.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="limitations_previous" title="Limitations of Previous Traffic Filtering Efforts">
<section anchor="limitations_previous_ddos" title="Limitations in Previous DDoS Traffic Filtering Efforts">
<t>The popularity of traffic-based, denial-of-service (DoS) attacks,
   which often requires the network operator to be able to use traffic
   filters for detection and mitigation, brings with it requirements
   that are not fully satisfied by existing tools.
</t>
<t>
     Increasingly, DoS mitigation requires coordination among several
   service providers in order to be able to identify traffic source(s)
   and because the volumes of traffic may be such that they will
   otherwise significantly affect the performance of the network.
</t>
<t>
   Several techniques are currently used to control traffic filtering of
   DoS attacks.  Among those, one of the most common is to inject
   unicast route advertisements corresponding to a destination prefix
   being attacked (commonly known as remote triggered blackhole RTBH).
   One variant of this technique marks such route
   advertisements with a community that gets translated into a discard
   Next Hop by the receiving router.  Other variants attract traffic to
   a particular node that serves as a deterministic drop point.
</t>
<t>
   Using unicast routing advertisements to distribute traffic filtering
   information has the advantage of using the existing infrastructure
   and inter-AS communication channels.  This can allow, for instance, a
   service provider to accept filtering requests from customers for
   address space they own.
</t>
<t>
   There are several drawbacks, however.  An issue that is immediately
   apparent is the granularity of filtering control: only destination
   prefixes may be specified.  Another area of concern is the fact that
   filtering information is intermingled with routing information.
</t>
<t>
   The mechanism defined in this document is designed to address these
   limitations.  We use the Flow Specification NLRI defined above to
   convey information about traffic filtering rules for traffic that
   is subject to modified forwarding behavior (actions). The actions
   are defined as extended communities and include (but are not limited
   to) rate-limiting (including discard), traffic redirection, packet
   rewriting.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="limitations_previous_mpls_ddos" title="Limitations in Previous BGP/MPLS Traffic Filtering Efforts">
<t>
   Provider-based Layer 3 VPN networks, such as the ones using a BGP/
   MPLS IP VPN <xref target="RFC4364"></xref> control plane, may have different traffic filtering
   requirements than Internet service providers.
</t>
<t>
   In these environments, the VPN customer network often has traffic
   filtering capabilities towards their external network connections
   (e.g., firewall facing public network connection).  Less common is
   the presence of traffic filtering capabilities between different VPN
   attachment sites.  In an any-to-any connectivity model, which is the
   default, this means that site-to-site traffic is unfiltered.
</t>
<t>
   In circumstances where a security threat does get propagated inside
   the VPN customer network, there may not be readily available
   mechanisms to provide mitigation via traffic filter.
</t>
<t>
But also Internet service providers may use those VPNs for scenarios like
having the Internet routing table in a VRF. Therefore, limitations described
in <xref target="limitations_previous_ddos"></xref> also apply to this section.
</t>
<t>The BGP Flow Specification addresses these limitations.
</t>
</section>
</section>
<section title="Traffic Monitoring">
<t>
   Traffic filtering applications require monitoring and traffic
   statistics facilities.  While this is an implementation-specific
   choice, implementations SHOULD provide:
   <list style="symbols">
   <t> A mechanism to log the packet header of filtered traffic.
   </t>
   <t>A mechanism to count the number of matches for a given flow
      specification rule.
   </t>
   </list>
  </t>
</section>
<section anchor="errorhandling" title="Error-Handling">
  <t>
      Error handling according to <xref target="RFC7606"></xref> SHOULD
      apply to this specification.
  </t>
    <t>
        This document introduces Traffic Filtering Action Extended Communities.
        Malformed Traffic Filtering Action Extended Communities in the sense of <xref target="RFC7606"></xref>
        Section 7.14. are Extended Community values that cannot be decoded according
        to <xref target="traffic_filtering_actions" /> of this specification.
    </t>
</section>
<section anchor="future_extensions" title="Future NLRI Extensions">
    <t>
      Future Flow Specification extensions may introduce new Flow
      Specification components. In order to facilitate such extensions of
      the Flow Specification NLRI, in addition to the cases described in
      <xref target="RFC7606"></xref>, if BGP encounters an unknown Flow
      Specification component in an UPDATE message, it SHOULD also treat
      this message as Treat-as-withdraw as specified in
      <xref target="RFC7606"></xref> Section 2.
  </t>
  <t>
    Such extensions SHOULD also specify a way to encode an "always-match" match condition within
    the newly introduced components (this is a match condition, encoded with the newly introduced components:
    If present on its own, matches all flows). This match condition can be used to propagate (and apply)
    certain filters only if a specific extension is known to the implemenation.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>
    This section complies with <xref target="RFC7153"></xref>.
  </t>
  <section title="AFI/SAFI Definitions">
    <t>
      IANA maintains a registry entitled "SAFI Values". For the purpose of this
      work, IANA is asked to update the following SAFIs according to the table below:
    </t>
    <texttable anchor="iana_safi" title="Registry: SAFI Values">
          <ttcol align="left">Value</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
          <c>133</c>   <c>IPv4 dissemination of Flow Specification rules</c>  <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>134</c>   <c>VPNv4 dissemination of Flow Specification rules</c>       <c>[this document]</c>
    </texttable>
  </section>
    <section title="Renaming of Experimental Use Registries">
        <t>IANA is asked to rename the registry entitled "Generic
            Transitive Experimental Use Extended Community Part 2 Sub-Types" to
            "Generic Transitive Extended Community Part 2 Sub-Types" and
            update the reference for this registry to [this document].
        </t>
        <t>IANA is asked to rename the registry entitled "Generic
            Transitive Experimental Use Extended Community Part 3 Sub-Types" to
            "Generic Transitive Extended Community Part 3 Sub-Types" and
            update the reference for this registry to [this document].
        </t>
    </section>
  <section title="Flow Component Definitions">
    <t>
      A Flow Specification consists of a sequence of flow components, which
      are identified by a an 8-bit component type. IANA has created and maintains
      a registry entitled "Flow Spec Component Types". IANA is asked to
      update the reference for this registry to [this document]. Furthermore the
      references to the values should be updated according to the table below.
    </t>

    <texttable anchor="iana_flow_component_types" title="Registry: Flow Spec Component Types">
          <ttcol align="left">Value</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
          <c>1</c>   <c>Destination Prefix</c>  <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>2</c>   <c>Source Prefix</c>       <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>3</c>   <c>IP Protocol</c>         <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>4</c>   <c>Port</c>                <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>5</c>   <c>Destination port</c>    <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>6</c>   <c>Source port</c>         <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>7</c>   <c>ICMP type</c>           <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>8</c>   <c>ICMP code</c>           <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>9</c>   <c>TCP flags</c>           <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>10</c>  <c>Packet length</c>       <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>11</c>  <c>DSCP</c>                <c>[this document]</c>
          <c>12</c>  <c>Fragment</c>            <c>[this document]</c>
    </texttable>
    <t>
      In order to manage the limited number space and accommodate several
      usages, the following policies defined by <xref target="RFC8126" />
      are used:
    </t>
    <texttable anchor="iana_flow_component_types_policies" title="Flow Spec Component Types Policies">
          <ttcol align="left">Type Values</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Policy</ttcol>
          <c>0</c>           <c>Specification required</c>
          <c>[1 .. 12]</c>   <c>Defined by this specification</c>
          <c>[13 .. 127]</c>   <c>Specification required</c>
          <c>[128 .. 255]</c>   <c>First Come First Served</c>
    </texttable>
    <t>
      The specification of a particular "Flow Spec Component Type" must clearly
      identify what the criteria used to match packets forwarded by the
      router is.  This criteria should be meaningful across router hops and
      not depend on values that change hop-by-hop such as TTL or Layer 2
      encapsulation.
    </t>
  </section>
 <section title="Extended Community Flow Specification Actions">
 <t>The Extended Community Flow Specification Action types defined in this document
   consist of two parts:
   <list>
     <t>Type (BGP Transitive Extended Community Type)</t>
     <t>Sub-Type</t>
   </list>
 </t>


   <t>
     For the type-part, IANA maintains a registry entitled "BGP Transitive Extended Community
     Types". For the purpose of this work (<xref
     target="traffic_filtering_actions" />), IANA is asked to update the
     references to the following values according to the table below:
   </t>
   <texttable anchor="iana_ext_comm_types" title="Registry: Generic Transitive Experimental Use Extended Community Types">
         <ttcol align="left">Type Value</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
         <c>0x81</c>
         <c>
           Generic Transitive Extended Community Part 2 (Sub-Types are
           defined in the "Generic Transitive Extended Community Part 2
           Sub-Types" Registry)
         </c>
         <c>[this document] [See Note-1] </c>

         <c>0x82</c>
         <c>
           Generic Transitive Extended Community Part 3
           (Sub-Types are defined in the "Generic Transitive
           Extended Community Part 3 Sub-Types" Registry)
         </c>
         <c>[this document] [See Note-1] </c>

   </texttable>

   <t>Note-1: This document obsoletes RFC7674.</t>
   <t>
     For the sub-type part of the extended community actions IANA maintains
     the following registries. IANA is asked to update all references
     according to the tables below and assign a new value for the "Flow spec
     traffic-rate-packets" Sub-Type.
   </t>
   <texttable anchor="iana_ext_comm_subtypes" title="Registry: Generic Transitive Experimental Use Extended Community Sub-Types">
         <ttcol align="left">Sub-Type Value</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
         <c>0x06</c>
         <c>
           Flow spec traffic-rate-bytes
         </c>
         <c>[this document]</c>

         <c>TBD</c>
         <c>
           Flow spec traffic-rate-packets
         </c>
         <c>[this document]</c>

         <c>0x07</c>
         <c>
           Flow spec traffic-action (Use of the "Value" field is defined in the "Traffic Action Fields" registry)
         </c>
         <c>[this document] [See Note-2]</c>

         <c>0x08</c>
         <c>
           Flow spec rt-redirect AS-2byte format
         </c>
         <c>[this document]</c>

         <c>0x09</c>
         <c>
           Flow spec traffic-remarking
         </c>
         <c>[this document]</c>

   </texttable>
   <t>Note-2: This document obsoletes both RFC7674 and RFC5575. </t>

   <texttable anchor="iana_ext_comm_subtypes2" title="Registry: Generic Transitive Extended Community Part 2 Sub-Types (has been renamed above)">
         <ttcol align="left">Sub-Type Value</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
         <c>0x08</c>
         <c>
           Flow spec rt-redirect IPv4 format
         </c>
         <c>[this document] [See Note-3] </c>
   </texttable>
   <texttable anchor="iana_ext_comm_subtypes3" title="Registry: Generic Transitive Extended Community Part 3 Sub-Types (has been renamed above)">
         <ttcol align="left">Sub-Type Value</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
         <c>0x08</c>
         <c>
           Flow spec rt-redirect AS-4byte format
         </c>
         <c>[this document] [See Note-3] </c>
   </texttable>
   <t> Note-3: This document obsoletes RFC7674, and becomes the only reference for this table.
   </t>
   <t>
     The "traffic-action" extended community (<xref
     target="traffic_action_subtype" />) defined in this document has 46 unused bits,
     which can be used to convey additional meaning. IANA
     created and maintains a new registry entitled: "Traffic Action
     Fields".  IANA is asked to update the reference for this registry to
     [this document]. Furthermore IANA is asked to update the references according to the table below.
     These values should be assigned via IETF Review rules only.
   </t>
   <texttable anchor="iana_traffic_action_subtype" title="Registry: Traffic Action Fields">
         <ttcol align="left">Bit</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
         <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
         <c>47</c><c>Terminal Action</c><c>[this document]</c>
         <c>46</c><c>Sample</c><c>[this document]</c>
   </texttable>
</section>
</section>
  <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security_considerations">
   <t>Inter-provider routing is based on a web of trust.  Neighboring
   autonomous systems are trusted to advertise valid reachability
   information.  If this trust model is violated, a neighboring
   autonomous system may cause a denial-of-service attack by advertising
   reachability information for a given prefix for which it does not
   provide service. Possible mitigations are <xref target="RFC6811" /> and
       <xref target="RFC8205" />.
   </t>
   <t> As long as traffic filtering rules are restricted to match the
   corresponding unicast routing paths for the relevant prefixes, the security
   characteristics of this proposal are equivalent to the existing security
   properties of BGP unicast routing. Any relaxation of the validation
   procedure described in <xref target="validation_procedure" /> may
   allow unwanted Flow Specification rules to be propagated and thus unwanted filter
   actions may be applied to flows.
    </t>
    <t>
   This document specifies
   traffic filtering actions that may need custom additional verification on the
   receiver side. See <xref target="operational_sc" />.
   </t>
   <t>  Where the above mechanisms are not in place, this would open the door
   to further denial-of-service attacks such as unwanted traffic filtering,
   remarking or redirection.
   </t>
   <t> Enabling firewall-like capabilities in routers without centralized
   management could make certain failures harder to diagnose.  For
   example, it is possible to allow TCP packets to pass between a pair
   of addresses but not ICMP packets.  It is also possible to permit
   packets smaller than 900 or greater than 1000 bytes to pass between a
    pair of addresses, but not packets whose length is in the range 900-
   1000.  Such behavior may be confusing and these capabilities should
   be used with care whether manually configured or coordinated through
   the protocol extensions described in this document.
  </t>
  <t>
      Flow Specification BGP speakers (e.g. automated DDoS controllers) not properly programmed,
      algorithms that are not performing as expected, or simply rogue systems
      may announce unintended Flow Specification filters, send updates at a high rate
      or generate a high number of Flow Specification filters.
      This may stress the receiving systems, exceed their maximum capacity or
      may lead to unwanted filter actions being applied to flows.
  </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Operational Security Considerations" anchor="operational_sc">
    <t> While the general verification of the traffic filter NLRI
    is specified in this document (<xref target="validation_procedure" />) the traffic filtering
    actions received by a third party may need custom verification or filtering. In particular
    all non traffic-rate actions may allow a third party to modify packet forwarding properties and potentially
    gain access to other routing-tables/VPNs or undesired queues. This can be avoided by proper filtering of action communities
    at network borders and by mapping user-defined communities (see <xref target="traffic_filtering_actions" />)
    to expose certain forwarding properties to third parties.
    </t>
    <t>
      Since verfication of the traffic filtering NLRI is tied to the announcement of
      the best unicast route, a unfiltered address space hijack (e.g. advertisement
      of a more specific route) may cause this verification to fail and consequently
      prevent Flow Specification filters from being accepted by a peer.
    </t>
  </section>
	<section title="Original authors">
	<t>Barry Greene,  Pedro Marques, Jared Mauch, Danny McPherson,
	and Nischal Sheth were authors on RFC5575, and therefore
	are contributing authors on this document.
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Acknowledgements">
   <t>The authors would like to thank Yakov Rekhter, Dennis Ferguson, Chris
   Morrow, Charlie Kaufman, and David Smith for their comments for the comments on
   the original RFC5575.  Chaitanya Kodeboyina
   helped design the flow validation procedure; and Steven Lin and Jim Washburn
   ironed out all the details necessary to
   produce a working implementation in the original RFC5575.
   </t>
   <t>
   A packet rate Flow Specification action was also described in a Flow Specification extension draft
   and the authors like to thank Wesley Eddy, Justin Dailey and Gilbert Clark for
   their work.
   </t>
   <t>Additionally, the authors would like to thank Alexander Mayrhofer, Nicolas Fevrier,
   Job Snijders, Jeffrey Haas and Adam Chappell for their comments and review.
   </t>
	</section>
  </middle>
  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC0791;
	  &RFC0793;
      &RFC2119;
	  &RFC2474;
      &RFC4271;
	  &RFC4360;
	  &RFC4364;
      &RFC4456;
	  &RFC4760;
	  &RFC5668;
	  &RFC7153;
	  &RFC7606;
    &RFC8126;
    &RFC8174;

    <reference anchor="ISO_IEC_9899">
        <front>
            <title>Information technology -- Programming languages -- C</title>
            <author>
                <organization>ISO</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="June" year="2018" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="9899:2018"/>
    </reference>
    <reference anchor="IEEE.754.1985">
        <front>
            <title>Standard for Binary Floating-Point Arithmetic</title>
            <author>
                <organization>IEEE</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="August" year="1985" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE" value="754-1985"/>
    </reference>
	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
	  &RFC4303;
	  &I-D.ietf-idr-flow-spec-v6;
      &RFC6811;
      &RFC8205;
    </references>
    <section title="Comparison with RFC 5575">
      <t>
        This document includes numerous editorial changes to RFC5575.
        It is recommended to read the entire document. The
        authors, however want to point out the following technical changes to
        RFC5575:
        <list>
          <t>
            <xref target="intro" /> introduces the Flow Specification NLRI. In
            RFC5575 this NLRI was defined as an opaque-key in BGPs database. This
            specification has removed all references to a opaque-key property.
           BGP is able to understand the NLRI encoding. This
            change also resulted in a new section regarding error-handling and
            extensibility (<xref target="errorhandling" /> and <xref target="future_extensions" />).
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="type_3" /> defines a numeric operator and comparison
            bit combinations. In RFC5575 the meaning of those
            bit combination was not explicitly defined and left open to the
            reader.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="type_3" /> - <xref target="type_8" />, <xref
            target="type_10" />, <xref target="type_11" /> make use of the above
            numeric operator. The allowed length of the comparison value was not
            consistently defined in RFC5575.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="traffic_filtering_actions" /> defines all traffic
            action extended communities as transitive extended communities.
            RFC5575 defined the traffic-rate action to be
            non-transitive and did not define the transitivity of the other
            action communities at all.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="traffic_rate_in_packets" /> introduces a new traffic
            filtering action (traffic-rate-packets). This action did not exist
            in RFC5575.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="rt_redirect_action_subtype" /> contains the same
            redirect actions already defined in RFC5575
            however, these actions have been renamed  to "rt-redirect" to make
            it clearer that the redirection is based on route-target.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="rules_action_interference" /> contains general
            considerations on interfering traffic actions.
            <xref target="traffic_action_subtype" /> also
            cross-references this section. RFC5575 did not mention this.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="errorhandling" /> contains new error handling.
          </t>
          <t>
            <xref target="future_extensions" /> describes graceful handling
              of unknown Flow Specification components to allow future extensions.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
  </rfc>
